Finding Aid for Jan BenDor papers, 1974-2005
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Jan BenDor papers 1974-2005 1988-1992
BenDor, Jan.
2010190 Aa 2; UAl
Ann Arbor-area women’s rights activist; research files, records related to her involvement in Safe House, an Ann Arbor women’s shelter, and papers related to her involvement in United Auto Workers-Technical Office Professionals Local 1976.
9 linear feet
1 oversize folders
1 phonograph records
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Material donated by Jan BenDor (donor number 10332 ) in March, 2010.
Periodic additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Jan BenDor (1946-) is known primarily for her work in the area of women's rights. She hold a Master of Social Work degree from the University of Michigan, and is ABD in the University of Michigan's doctoral program in psychology. She currently works as a social worker, and teaches as an adjunct at Eastern Michigan University.
As founder of the Women's Crisis Center in Ann Arbor, she was responsible for starting the rape crisis center movement in Michigan. She was also instrumental in lobbying for the passage of the Criminal Sexual Conduct Law reform of 1974. Additionally, she helped to initiate some of the nation's first training programs about domestic violence for police, prosecutors, and hospital staff. Other accomplishments include organizing a boycott against Domino's Pizza for its anti-woman policies, and working within the mental health community to end sexism, provide better support for survivors of abuse and sexual assault, and educate young men and offenders about women's issues. She has also been a member of the Board of Trustees of Safe House, an Ann Arbor shelter for battered women (1988-2004).
She has also been active in local government and the Eastern Michigan University United Auto Workers-Technical Office Professionals (UAW-TOP) union, serving for over a decade as a Trustee, Planning Commissioner, and Deputy Township Clerk for Pittsfield Township and as Vice President of UAW-TOP Local 1976. In her capacity as a local government official she has supported efforts to preserve green space, to establish long term plans for the maintenance of public services, to implement measures to help prevent predatory loans, and to reform elections laws and promote voter registration.
Currently, BenDor lives in Ypsilanti, Michigan with her husband, and is the mother of two adult sons. She continues to work in the field of human services, and remains active in her support of women's issues and local government.
The collection consists of seven series: Tom Monaghan, University of Michigan, Women’s Crisis Center, Safe House, United Auto Workers, Rape Law Task Force and Posters. The papers include both research files, notes, collected materials, and records of local organizations of which BenDor was a member. The collection’s strength lies in its documentation of BenDor’s activities on behalf of women’s rights.
Subjects:
BenDor, Jan.; Monaghan, Tom, 1937-; Domino's Pizza (Firm); Eastern Michigan University.; Safe House (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Women's Crisis Center (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Abused women--Services for--Michigan.; Labor disputes--Michigan--Ypsilanti.
- Tom Monaghan
  The first series Tom Monaghan consists mostly of collected materials and research notes compiled by BenDor from 1975 to 1993. The files include newspaper clippings, research notes, and publications related to Tom Monaghan's role as the founder of Domino's Pizza, owner of the Detroit Tigers. There are also substantial materials related to his religious and personal life, especially his involvement in the Word of God Catholic charismatic movement.
  - Domino's Pizza
    - 990 Tax Return Correspondence 1991 (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor News, Boycott Stories, 1991 (Box 1)
    - Dave Black, Other People 1990-1991 (Box 1)
    - Domino's Financial Information 1990, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Domino's Foundation Information 1986-1989, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Domino's Sale 1989-1990 (Box 1)
    - Domino's Corporation 1980-1990 (scattered) (Box 1)
    - Domino's Lawsuits 1991, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Domino's Franchise News Clippings 1991-1993 (Box 1)
    - NAACP Boycott 1989-1990 (Box 1)
    - People Against Dangerous Delivery (PADD) 1991 (Box 1)
    - Pizza Wars 1990-1991 (Box 1)
  - Religion
    - Catholicism General 1976-1990 (scattered), 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Covenant House Ritter 1990-1991 (Box 1)
    - Servant Ministries 1986-1987 (Box 1)
    - Catholic Campaign for America 1991 (Box 1)
    - The Covenant undated (Box 1)
    - Home Schooling 1989-1992 (Box 1)
    - Knights of Malta 1990 (Box 1)
    - Nicaragua Cathedral 1990 (Box 1)
    - Priest of St. Francis 1989-1990 (Box 1)
    - Religious Causes News Clippings 1991-1992 (Box 1)
    - Religion General 1984-1991 (scattered) (Box 1)
    - Shepherd's Guide, Christian Business Directory for Greater Ann Arbor/Washtenaw Co. 1989-1990 (Box 1)
    - Tom S. Monaghan at Madonna University 1990 (Box 1)
    - Word of God Clippings 1991 (Box 1)
    - Word of God Bentley Notes 1990 (Box 1)
    - Word of God History 1971-1990 (scattered) (Box 1)
    - Virgin Birth - Thomason-Cobb controversy 1989-1990 (Box 1)
      (News clippings related to the Virgin Birth controversy at Ypsilanti High School involving teacher Sharon Cobb and parent Peter Thomason)
    - "All of Your People," The Word of God (Box 1)
  - Detroit Tigers Ownership
    - Miscellaneous 1990-1991 (Box 1)
    - Tigers News Clippings 1990-1992, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Other
    - Agenda, Washtenaw County's Alternative Newsmonthly, 1989 (Box 1)
    - Ann Arbor Real Estate 1990 (Box 1)
    - Arts Magazine 1990 (Box 1)
    - Belknap Other Franchises 1991 (Box 1)
    - Book Publisher 1982-1986 (Box 2)
    - Cable Television 1989 (Box 2)
    - Christmas Lights 1987-1989 (Box 2)
    - Consider Magazine, 1990 (Box 2)
    - Criticisms undated (Box 2)
    - Data Packets 1989 (Box 2)
    - Dixboro School 1988-1989 (Box 2)
    - Drummond Island 1989-1990 (Box 2)
    - John E. Fetzer 1975, 1989 (Box 2)
      (Owner of Detroit Tigers from 1961 to 1983)
    - Group 243, Inc. 1991 (Box 2)
      (Ann Arbor advertising agency)
    - Ronald A. Hingst Letter to the Editor re: "Tom Monaghan has Domino Effect on his sports venture" in Livingston County Press, 1990 (Box 2)
    - Interview, Business Monthly 1990 (Box 2)
    - Investigation 1988-1989, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Legal, 1990-91 (Box 2)
    - Marjory Murphy Letter to the Editor re: McNeil-Lehrer News Hour segment on Tom Monaghan February 2, 1990 (Box 2)
    - Marriott 1989-1990 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous 1985-1987 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous News Magazines 1992-1993 (Box 2)
    - Monaghan Personal News Clippings 1991-1992 (Box 2)
    - National Catholic Reporter 1975-1988 (scattered) (Box 2)
    - New House 1990-1991 (Box 2)
    - Non-Profit Reports 1985-1991 (Box 2)
    - Notes 1990-1991 (Box 2)
    - Note Cards about Monaghan 1991 (Box 2)
    - O'Connor Sports Medicine 1987 (Box 2)
    - People's Campaign for Choice 1988, 2 folders (Box 2)
      (includes photo negatives)
    - Political Contributions and Activity 1988-1990, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Possessions 1987, 1990 (Box 2)
    - Publications 1985-1988 (Box 2)
    - Reindeer Meat 1991 (Box 2)
      (News clipping on Dominos pizza use of Reindeer meat sausage on pizzas in Alaska)
    - Right Wing 1984-1990 (scattered) (Box 2)
    - Schools 1990-1991 (Box 2)
    - Tom Monaghan's Honors 1989, 1991 (Box 2)
    - USA Weekend, 1990 (Box 2)
    - Wichita 1991 (Box 2)
- University of Michigan
  University of Michigan, the second series, consists of news clippings and notes related to President James Duderstadt and Trustees Eugene and Sarah Power.
  - James Duderstadt 1987-1990 (scattered), 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Eugene Power 1978-1991 (scattered) (Box 2)
  - Press on Sarah Power's Death 1987 (Box 2)
  - Research Notes from Bentley Library re University of Michigan Regent Sarah Goddard Power 1989-1990 (Box 2)
- Women's Crisis Center
  The third series, Women's Crisis Center, provides documentation of the Crisis Center's activities from 1989 to 2000. The materials include publications, news clippings, and information on the treatment of sexual assault victims.
  - Abortion Protest News Clippings 1989-1990 (Box 2)
  - Crisis Center Publications 1974 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous News Clippings 1998-2000 (Box 2)
  - Treatment of Sexual Assault Victims undated (Box 2)
  - Washtenaw Rescue Legal Poll, 1990-91 (Box 2)
- Safe House
  The fourth series, Safe House, document's BenDor's involvement in this Ann Arbor-area women's shelter. Materials include minutes and supplemental files from Board Meetings, Annual Reports, personnel committee files, and staff and Board of Trustees manuals.
  - Board Meetings
    - 1988 (Box 3)
    - 1989, 5 folders (Box 3)
    - 1990, 5 folders (Box 3)
    - 1991, 5 folders (Box 3)
    - 1992, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - 1993, 4 folders (Box 4)
    - 1994, 4 folders (Box 4)
    - 1995, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - 1996, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - 1997 (Box 4)
    - 1998 (Box 4)
    - 1999, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - 2000, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - 2001 (Box 5)
    - 2002, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - 2003 (Box 5)
    - 2004, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Annual Reports, Financial and OMB Circular A-133
    - 2000 (Box 5)
    - 2002-2003 (Box 5)
  - Other Administrative Files
    - Brochures, Pamphlets and Letters about Domestic Violence 1984-2005 (Box 5)
    - Staff Handbooks 1993-2004 (Box 5)
    - Job Descriptions and Personnel Count 1990-2002 (scattered) (Box 5)
    - Personnel Committee 2004, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Manuals
    - Staff Manuals
      - 1988-1989 (Box 5)
      - 1997, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - 2003, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Board of Trustees Manual
      - 1988-1989, 4 folders (Box 6)
- United Auto Workers
  United Auto Workers-Technical Office Professionals, the final series, documents BenDor's involvement in UAW-TOP Local 1976 in the late 1980s and early 1990s. In particular, it includes news clippings and ephemera related to staff layoffs at Eastern Michigan University (EMU) in 1992. Other materials include meeting minutes, publicity files, and information about worker grievances at EMU.
  - All Union Council Budget Issues 1993, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Announcements and Press 1990 (Box 6)
  - Budget 1989-1993 (Box 6)
  - Committee Reports 1981-1990, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Eastern Michigan University Contract and Lay-Off Negotiations 1990-1993 (Box 6)
  - Eastern Michigan University, Professional and Technical Employees Laid Off 1992 (Box 6)
  - Peter Friedlander 1990 (Box 6)
    (Re: Friedlander's class at Wayne State University, Labor and Society: A Rank and File Perspective)
  - Local 1796, 1990 (Box 6)
  - Local 1796 Contract, To Do, 1989 (Box 6)
  - The Looting 1992, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous UAW Ephemera 1991-1993 (Box 6)
  - New Directions 1989-1992, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Newsletters 1990-1992 (Box 6)
  - Players 1990 (Box 6)
  - Presidential Delegates and Dates 1992 (Box 6)
  - Reference Materials 1991, undated (Box 6)
  - Retreat 1990-1991 (Box 6)
  - Stewards Meeting 1991-1992 (Box 6)
  - Technical Office Professional (T. O. P.) Convention 1991 (Box 6)
  - T. O. P. Council Meetings 1990 (Box 6)
  - Unfair Labor Practices 1990 (Box 6)
  - United Auto Workers Campaign 1989-1992 (Box 6)
  - UAW-related News Clippings 1991-1995 (Box 6)
  - World War III 1987-1992 (Box 6)
- Rape Law Task Force 1974-1975
  - Resource materials and other files relating to her work on the Task Force leading up to the passage of Michigan’s Criminal Sexual Conduct Law (Public Act 266) 1974-1975 (Box 7)
  - Resource materials and other files relating to her work on the Task Force leading up to the passage of Michigan’s Criminal Sexual Conduct Law (Public Act 266) 1974-1975 (Box 8)
    (continued)
  - Resource materials and other files relating to her work on the Task Force leading up to the passage of Michigan’s Criminal Sexual Conduct Law (Public Act 266) 1974-1975 (Box 9)
- Posters
  - "Unity in Oppression" undated (Folder 1)
  - "Freedom to Choose?" undated (Folder 1)
  - Dominos Farm Enterprises (Folder 1)